All right good morning today is the 19th of תשרי Tishrei the
21st of October and today's דף daf is בבא מציעא Bava Metziah
כ"ה Kaf Hey and we're going to start right at the bottom
of כ"ד עמוד ב' Kaf Dalet Amud Bet we have a very
interesting משנה mishna which is a direct parallel to the first משנה
mishna in אלו מציאות Elu Metzios the first משנה mishna said אלו
מציאות שלו Elu metzios shelo these are all the things you get
to keep if you find them and we determined that for the
most part it's because they lack any identifiable סימן siman and here
we have the flip we have very similar or parallel types of
objects that in this case do have a סימן siman and therefore
will be אלו חייב להכריז elu chayav lehachriz these are the ones
that a person if you find them you have to announce them
we're starting right at the משנה mishna at the bottom of כ"ד
עמוד ב' Kaf Dalet Amud Bet sorry Rabbi Linzer isn't here today
it's all my fault so the משנה mishna says ואלו חייב להכריז
Ve-elu chayav lehachriz these are the types of objects that a person
has to announce if you find them that is you have an
obligation to return them to the owner rather than keep them yourself
and what are they מצא פירות בכלי Matza peirot bekli if you
found fruit in a כלי kli in a vessel
interesting to note right we saw the previous משנה mishna had פירות
מפוזרות peirot mefuzarot so each of these cases for the most part
is going to be directly parallel to the previous משנה mishna מצא
פירות בכלי Matza peirot bekli או כלי כמותו o kli kemoto or
just a vessel by itself even without the fruit meaning for the
most part fruits we understand or whatever it is produce grain it
might be or any kind of fruit don't have any kind of
סימן siman so the fact that the produce is in a כלי
kli becomes its defining סימן siman but the כלי kli itself also
has its own סימנים simanim because every כלי kli for the most
part is going to be different yes
in neither this משנה mishna nor the first one in the chapter
is there any specific explicit mention of סימנים simanim
correct and that's what's partially what's so interesting about learning משניות Mishnayot
as an independent body compared to studying משנה mishna as part of
the Talmud is that very often the underlying core principles that אמוראים
Amoraim are able to tease out of the משנה mishna are not
explicitly discussed in the משניות Mishnayot משניות Mishnayot address the laws themselves
but maybe not the motivation and so we actually don't have the
terminology of סימנים simanim we see that we're going to see סימנים
simanim there's a whole מחלוקת machloket about סימנים simanim סימנים דאורייתא simanim
de-oraisa סימנים דרבנן simanim de-rabbanan and things like that all of that
comes out of
this discussion of סימנים simanim is entirely implicit in the משנה mishna
it's not mentioned
explicitly כלי כמותו kli kemoto we saw also the difference this must
be a different kind of a כלי kli than a כלי אנפוריא
kli anpuria right because a כלי אנפוריא kli anpuria we said does
not have any סימן siman so this must be a כלי kli
that does have סימנים simanim or מעות בכיס ma'ot bekis if you
found coins in a wallet now you have to remember wallet back
then wasn't a wallet wallet but it was basically just a small
little bag you often see like in Shakespeare and things you hear
men talk about their purse purse just means a pouch to hold
your money or something like that so it was again some kind
of a container
i always like going on little tangents into טהרות Taharos
so there's a הלכה halacha about a flat piece of leather or
rawhide that's used to bundle up coins צר המעות tzor hama'ot is
not actually a כיס kis it's not actually a כלי kli in
and of itself but if it's used to hold coins well if
it's צר המעות tzor hama'ot it's טהור tahor because you're always opening
and closing it if you have your wallet even if it's made
of rawhide but it's not really a כלי kli if it's just
a flat piece of leather because it's never closed and it doesn't
retain its shape but צר המרגלית tzor hamargalit if it's a pouch
that you've made out of rawhide to hold gems well then you're
never opening up your gems your gems are like your savings account
so you close it up and you leave it there so it
retains its shape and then you would say טמא tamei or really
it's a מחלוקת תנאי machloket tannai again
but if you find this in a place where רבים rabbim are
really going through you can keep it as
we saw before even in a place where if there are totally
רבים rabbim going and the סימן siman is going to be either
unrecognizable or that the person will already have had יאוש ye'ush all
of that is going to be trumping that discussion but here these
are sort of our basic assumptions about סימנים simanim before we get
into the broader יאוש ye'ush discussion and you know for example the
זוטו של ים zuto shel yam and things like that obviously או
כיס כמותו o kis kemoto or the wallet by itself even without
any money in it we're going to see the גמרא's Gemara main
question is going to be why why do these discussions come up
both both of them together that is if we knew that you
would find it with the fruit inside or with the money inside
then why would we not know then that you also have to
just the container or just the כיס kis ציבורי פירות tziburei peirot
or piles of fruit or ציבורי מעות tziburei ma'ot piles of
coins so those are two other kind of things that is not
מפוזרות mefuzarot Scattered, but either in כלים, keilim, the כלי kli by
itself, or in a well-defined pile. The גמרא Gemara is going to
discuss what kind of pile are we talking about and how many
piles and also שלושה מטבעות זה על גב זה. shlosha matbe'ot zeh
al gab zeh. Three coins one on top of the other. There's
going to be discussion what kind of a shape are we talking
about when we say three coins one on top of the other.
One of the things I was thinking about this morning, this just
interesting to me, is how difficult it can be for the משנה
Mishnah and the גמרא Gemara sometimes to illustrate for us a visual
in words, right? I mean you go back to the first משנה
Mishnah in שס Shas in ברכות, Berachot, the discussion, or second משנה
Mishnah in ברכות Berachot maybe is better example, how do you describe
sunrise? How early is early in the morning and not late at
night? So you have to describe a color change.
Definitely don't go earlier.
Or you have to describe the color of the sky or how
bright it is outside. These are things that are very difficult to
put into words. It would be very easy if they could just
take a picture. So שלושה מטבעות זה על גב זה shlosha matbe'ot
zeh al gab zeh also just be easier if they would show
us a picture of it, three one on top of the other.
We're going to have to see. So כריכות krichot ברשות היחיד birshut
hayachid or bundles of straw that have been in רשות היחיד reshut
hayachid because we saw the previous משנה Mishnah was ברשות הרבים birshut
harabim where the סימן siman would have been presumed to have been
damaged by people trampling on it and things like that וככרות של
בעל הבית vechikrot shel ba'al habayit and the loaves of a homeowner,
that is not the baker's bread which is all identical, but a
homeowner's bread, each of the loaves are going to be a little
bit different. I remember I made this חלה challah and I braided
it this way or it had a lump in it, had a
crack and it had this and that. So you can be more
familiar with the loaves of bread. Also presumably because a בעל הבית
ba'al habayit who's baking the bread has a smaller number of loaves,
so more familiarity with them in that way as well. Okay וגיזי
צמר vegizei tzemer הלקוחים מבית האומן halakuchim mibeit ha'uman or shearings of
wool that had been taken from the בית האומן beit ha'uman from
the laborer's house, from the manufacturer's house, meaning that they've already been
processed somewhat. We saw that the הלקוחים מן המדינה halakuchim min hamedina
if they're taken from the countryside, they've not been processed at all,
they have no סימן. siman. But once they've started to be processed,
there's a certain amount of סימן siman that comes along with that
processing. Okay כדי יין וכדי שמן kadei yayin vekadei shemen and also
jars of oil or jars of wine, אלו הרי אלו חייב להכריז.
elu harei elu chayav lehachriz. These a person if you find them,
you have to announce that you found it.
And so,
yes. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara is going to ask first question,
טעמא דמצא פירות בכלי. ta'ama dematza peirot bikli.
The fact that you have to return it as our משנה Mishnah
says is because you found the fruit in a container, in a
vessel, ומעות בכיס ume'ot bekis and coins in a wallet. Okay, however,
הא כלי ולפניו פירות כיס ולפניו מעות הרי אלו שלו. ha kli
ulfanav peirot kis ulfanav me'ot harei elu shelo.
It sounds like implicitly if the fruits were right next to the
container or the money was right next to the wallet. For example,
I will show you now. I have my wallet, I have a
twenty dollar bill, and if I found them like this, well that's
money next to the wallet, it's not the same as the money
being in the wallet. So we're going to have to see what.
So that's the implicit suggestion the גמרא Gemara makes from our משנה.
Mishnah. That is the reason you have to return it is because
the money was in the container or the fruits were in the
container. Interestingly, whenever we have two משניות mishnayot like this that have
two precise cases and they're being contrasted, well what about the gray
area in between? Money next to a wallet is not מעות מפוזרות,
ma'ot mefuzarot, it's not scattered. It's next to a wallet, but it's
not in the wallet, and that becomes a gray area kind of
a case. So the דיוק diyuk from our משנה Mishnah is that
that should be שלו, shelo, that a person who finds it can
keep it. תנינא להא דתנו רבנן. tanina leha detanu rabanan. So we
have a supporting ברייתא baraita for this based on this. מצא כלי
matza kli if you found a container ולפניו פירות ulfanav peirot and
the fruits are in front of it, או כיס ולפניו מעות o
kis ulfanav me'ot or a wallet and the coins are next to
it, הרי אלו שלו. harei elu shelo. Then you can keep them
because our משנה Mishnah is the directing הלכה. halacha. That is it's
only when it's in the wallet or in the container that the
person would have to announce it and find the owner. Okay, the
next clause of the ברייתא baraita says מקצתן בכלי ומקצתן על גבי
קרקע miktzatan bikli umiktzatan al gabei karka if part of them, some
of them were in the container and some of them were on
the ground, או מקצתן בכיס ומקצתן על גבי קרקע o miktzatan bekis
umiktzatan al gabei karka or the money some of it was in
the wallet and some was outside the wallet, חייב להכריז. chayav lehachriz.
You have to announce. That's very interesting. That is because in such
a case presumably you can assume that they spilled out. That is
the wallet still has some coins in it and there's some coins
next to it. So the coins that are outside fell out. Or
the fruits, I have a bucket of apples and there're a pile
of apples next to the bucket and there are some apples still
in the bucket. So I can understand or assume that the apples
that fell out must have fallen out of the כלי. kli. Yes,
Charlie?
Back in the first משנה Mishnah we had the case of
מעות מפוזרות. ma'ot mefuzarot. Exactly. It's sort of creating where the dividing
line would be.
Right. We have two sort of explicit cases that we know. We
know מפוזרות mefuzarot is so scattered that that it has no סימן.
siman. We know that if it's in a container or if it's
in a wallet, it has a סימן. siman. And the question is
where do you draw that line exactly? How do you determine the
boundary point between? And that becomes very interesting to think about the
fact that there has to be a well-defined point at which it
transitions from שלו shelo and חייב להכריז chayav l'hachriz because we're talking
about on the one hand there's a מצוה, mitzvah, מצות עשה mitzvot
aseh to return the lost object and there's also a מצות לא
תעשה, mitzvot lo ta'aseh, לא תוכל להתעלם, lo tuchal l'hitalem, you can't
ignore a lost object. So you can't say that that grey area
is just undefined because then maybe you're stealing it from someone who
it rightfully belongs to. Okay. And just an interesting point. What does
it mean חייב להכריז? chayav l'hachriz? חייב להכריז chayav l'hachriz for what?
Meaning we have two different things here. We have the fruit and
we have the fruit that was outside of the container and we
also have the container with the fruit still inside.
Say what, I found lost objects and whatever, you know, and you
can get both.
Okay, well so we're going to have to see. So the next,
the next ברייתא braita is being brought as a challenge. ורמינהו. u'raminhu.
We have a challenging ברייתא. braita. What does this ברייתא braita say?
מצא דבר שאין בו סימן בצד דבר שיש בו סימן. matza davar
she'ein bo siman b'tzad davar she'yesh bo siman. What if I found
two different things next to each other? One has a סימן siman
and one does not. That sounds like the fruits next to the
container that has fruits inside. Okay. And what's הלכה? halacha? חייב להכריז.
chayav l'hachriz. You have to announce it. Meaning so far so good
that it's not שלו. shelo. Meaning what did we say? We said
the fruits that were outside— outside of the— no, חייב להכריז. chayav
l'hachriz. So that so far so good but the challenge comes from
the סיפא seifa of the ברייתא. braita. What does it say? בא
בעל סימן, ba ba'al siman, if the person who claims a סימן
siman comes to collect his object ונטל את שלו, v'natal et shelo,
זכה הלה בדבר שאין בו סימן. zacha haleh b'davar she'ein bo siman.
Then the person who found the object can acquire the object that
did not have a סימן. siman. What happened? I had a כלי,
kli, right, and I had the fruits.
This has a סימן siman and this doesn't have a סימן. siman.
Right. So what happens? The person who can make a claim on
the vessel comes and takes it away. But he can only claim
the vessel. He can't also claim the fruit.
Does it matter if it's fallen out of the vessel or not?
It doesn't matter because it could be כלי כמות שהוא kli kemoto
shehu or כלי kli with פירות. peirot.
I'm probably saying this because I probably remember the גמרא. Gemara. But
like let's say it's like a tipped over thing you know then
we're going—that's the next discussion.
So that's going to be how do we reconcile, meaning what happens?
We had two different contradictory ברייתות. braitot. The first ברייתא braita says
you find a situation like this, fruits next to a container that
has fruits inside, the ברייתא braita said חייב להכריז. chayav l'hachriz. You
have to give it back. But the next ברייתא braita says it's
חייב להכריז chayav l'hachriz but sounds like only the כלי kli could
go back to the person with the סימן siman but the fruits
would be still fair game. Yes.
Is it in the case because he sets it's not—it's not his
on it down?
Ah, so that's already a resolution. Look at what it—meaning if you
look I think that's רש"י's Rashi's explanation. רש"י Rashi says, right, חייב
להכריז, chayav l'hachriz, so חייב להכריז על הכל. chayav l'hachriz al hakol.
You have to announce that you found everything and then what happens?
ויתנו המעות לבעל הכיס v'yitnu hamaot l'ba'al hakis and you would give
the coins to the wallet owner. And then the next רש"י, Rashi,
בא בעל סימן ונטל את שלו את הכיס ואמר אין המעות שלי
זכה הלה במעות. ba ba'al siman v'natal et shelo et hakis v'amar
ein hamaot sheli zacha haleh b'maot.
רש"י Rashi has a very different read of the גמרא. Gemara. רש"י's
Rashi's point is that the בעל הכיס ba'al hakis only claims this
or the or the בעל הכלי ba'al hakli only claims that he
had three apples.
Well, he could show up and he says, meaning what happens? I
say I found apples and an apple barrel. And now the guy
comes and says that's my apple barrel, here's the סימן. siman. And
he says, and I ask, you know, how many apples were there?
He says there were three apples. There weren't eight apples? That's an
interesting question. So רש"י's Rashi's already reading in an interesting point which
is that now he's taken this away because he's not even claiming
this. It seems like the way I initially read the גמרא Gemara
is that actually he doesn't get to make a claim about these
fruits because these fruits have no סימן siman even though they're next
to the כלי. kli. So that becomes a very interesting question. Are
they considered together? Are they considered two מציאות? metziot?
Or he could have said I found eight of them, three were
in and five were out.
Well but you need to keep some secrets for yourself to be
able to have test the test the claimant.
If he says apples and fruit or he says I found a
כלי kli and fruit. Okay well the כלי kli was three inside
and five right next to it.
Right. So but the point is that רש"י Rashi says very interesting
thing, רש"י Rashi says חייב להכריז על הכל, chayav l'hachriz al hakol,
you have to announce that you found everything and that the בעל
הכלי ba'al hakli presumably at least has the power to initially make
a claim on everything and only if he agrees that he does
not have rights to the fruits, then the finder finders keepers for
the fruit. Okay. אמר רב זביד. Amar Rav Zevid. So רב זביד
Rav Zevid said, לא קשיא, la kashya, so these two ברייתות braitot
do not contradict. and that the בעל הכלי Ba’al HaKli presumably at
least has the power to initially make a claim on everything and
only if he agrees that he does not have rights to the
fruit, then the finder, finders keepers for the fruit. Okay. אמר רב
זביד. Amar Rav Zvid. So רב זביד Rav Zvid said: לא קשיא,
La kashya, these two ברייתות baraitot do not contradict. Why? So just
to highlight what was the contradiction: The contradiction was that on the
one hand, we said חייב להכריז, chayav lehachriz, if you found a
situation like this, you would have to announce all of it, and
the other hand the ברייתא braita said you would have to announce
all of it, but you would still be able to keep these
ones after the בעל הכלי Ba’al HaKli took his כלי kli away.
רש"י Rashi already is trying to mesh the two ברייתות. baraitot. That
is, רש"י Rashi read the rest of the גמרא Gemara and is
telling us, but our initial read of the ברייתא braita sees them
as contradictory.
You look at it as if in the first ברייתא braita it
says to me anyway, it says as if when you announce on
everything
the פירות peirot that are on the street is part of the
סימן. siman. Right,
in a sense. Right, so you're describing the
situation
by—well we're going to see is מקום, makom, סימן, siman, right, all-
all of those questions, right? So those come up.
We've had why is there a dispute between these two ברייתות? baraitot?
The first one just doesn't—the second one continues where the first one
left off, it appears.
Ah, okay. So it sounds like the second one qualifies or- or
adds precision to the case in the first ברייתא, braita, but whenever
we have one ברייתא braita that's more specific than the first, we-
we would presume the first one maybe, until we do that back
and forth, the first one you would assume is not talking about
that kind of a case, talking about a different kind of a
case or- or has a different resolution to that case. You don't
have to wait for the בעל הסימן Ba’al HaSiman at all. If
it's- if it was that way, I mean מצא—what matza was it?
The money is next to the כיס, kis, right? הרי אלו שלו.
Harei elu shelo. That if it was מקצתן בכלי ומקצתן על גבי
קרקע, miktzatan bikli umiktzatan al gabei karka, if it was split half
and half, then חייב להכריז, chayav lehachriz, you have to announce and
you would never get to keep any of it in this case
according to the first ברייתא braita it sounds like. Okay. So אמר
רב זביד לא קשיא, Amar Rav Zvid la kashya, it's not a
קשיא. kashya. הא בכובא דכיתנא, Ha bekuba dechitna, this is talking about
a- a box of flax. הא בצינא ופירי, Ha betzina upeirei, and
this is talking about a- a barrel of fruit. So what's going
to be the difference? Meaning, there's a difference between flax and—how easy
it is to spill out? How easy it is that it- for
it to spill out. Now רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot disagree about
how easy it is for flax to spill out of a barrel.
I think רש"י's פשט Rashi's peshat makes more sense. Okay. So maybe
we have to think more like this. But רש"י Rashi says that-
that the flax, because it's long and bunchy, if it fell out,
some of it will still stay in the barrel. That is, fruits,
because they're round, would all spill out all at once and they
would roll. But the flax, because it's a big bundle or a
big tangle of- of stalks, they're not going to fall out as
easily. So they'll still remain inside the container. And תוספות Tosafot thinks
the opposite. תוספות Tosafot says פשתן שקשור ביחד, pishtan shekashur beyachad, it
could be בכלי היה ונפל. bikli haya vanafal. The flax, all of
the flax would fall out as one big chunk according to תוספות.
Tosafot. The fact that it's tangled up means not that it stays
in the barrel, but that it all falls out of the barrel.
So, I don't know, you have to go by what the material
is and how tangly it is. It's just interesting to see that
they disagree about how they could stay in the container. So that
was רב זביד's Rav Zvid's answer. רב זביד Rav Zvid said in
the case where the person has no rights to it, it's because
it's very obvious that the fruit that fell out of the container
were assigned to that container initially and that some fell out and
some stayed in. But that fruit that would all fall out if
they fell out, well then the fruit next to the כלי kli
maybe didn't fall out because if they had tipped over and fallen
out, all of them would have fallen out. There would be nothing
left inside the כלי. kli. So the fact that there are fruit
inside the כלי kli proves that the fruit next to the כלי
kli were not in the כלי. kli. That's רב זביד's Rav Zvid's
answer.
רב פפא אמר—so
Rav
Pappa
amar what are we trying to say then? So what- so if
I found things, fruit, they were next to it, inside, they were
next to
it, incidentally of each other?
Well,
that's- that's the question. That's coming up, which is that in a
certain sense—I think actually רמב"ן Ramban may say that. No, it's the
אור שמח. Or Sameach. The אור שמח Or Sameach makes a claim
about that, which is basically that this whole סוגיא sugya seems to
be going against the general principle we know that if you have
רוב וקרוב, rov vekarov, if you have a majority situation and you
have something that's assigned based on proximity, usually we follow the רוב
rov over the קרוב. karov. So here we're not follow—here we actually
are assessing קרוב karov being a relevant factor. And the אור שמח
Or Sameach basically says because, yeah, it would be incredibly unlikely, like
it's already unlikely for people to lose things. That's like, you know,
whatever chance possibility do people lose their כלי kli of fruit? And
now you're presuming that two different people lost two different things right
next to each other, that's very unreasonable. So that's an interesting way
to analyze the situation. Okay, let's keep going.
Between the majority and minority, is there an additional factor that of
the vessel itself, does that change the equation?
Well,
so that's part of the question as well. That is, how much
are we talking about the majority of fruit in the world are
not in this vessel? So maybe these fruit we would assess by
that רוב. rov. But they're קרוב, karov, they're next to the
vessel, so maybe— רב פפא אמר, Rav Pappa amar, הא דהא בציני
פירי. ha de-ha b'tzinei pirei. No,
we're talking about a barrel of fruits in both cases. ולא קשיא,
Velo kashya, הא דאשתייר בה מידי, ha de-ishtayer ba midi, in this
case some remained in the container, הא דלא אשתייר בה מידי, ha
de-lo ishtayer ba midi, meaning it's not based on the type of
fruits or how they would get tangled, it's just in general. Did
it remain in the container or not? Okay. So he says ולא
קשיא, velo kashya, and the ואיבעית אימא, v'ibeit eima,
alternatively, that is an alternative explanation presumably ascribed to רב פפא, Rav
Pappa, though perhaps just left anonymous, ואיבעית אימא, v'ibeit eima, another way
to reconcile these, הא דהא דלא אשתייר בה מידי, ha de-ha de-lo
ishtayer ba midi, maybe nothing was left in either container. ולא קשיא,
Velo kashya, הא דמהדרי אפיה לגבי פירי, ha de-mahadrei apei legabei pirei,
in one case the mouth of the container, the empty container, is
next to the fruits, and one, it's the opposite direction. It's facing
away from the fruits. So that would be a better presumption about
in which case did the fruits roll out of the container. And
now to what we have the next one, ואיבעית אימא, v'ibeit eima,
הא דהא דמהדרי אפיה לגבי פירי, ha de-ha de-mahadrei apei legabei pirei,
in both cases it's where it is facing the fruits, but nonetheless,
around
the fruits, ולא קשיא, velo kashya,
הא דאית ליה אוגנין לצנא ha de-it lei ognin letzana והא דלית
ליה אוגנין לצנא. v'ha de-leit lei ognin letzana.
That is does the container have a lip, does the container have
a lid that's going to keep things from spilling out? So if
the container has a lip, then you can presume that if anything
would have tried to fall out of the container, meaning if you
find a closed container and fruit next to it, then there's no
way that the fruit fell out of the container because the lid
is still there. So that's going to be our point there. Okay.
We're at the...
It makes a lot more sense if it was on
a slope, which case it could... I'm sure we could make all
sorts of distinctions, we have a lot of גמרא Gemara more to
cover, so let's keep going. Okay. ציבורי פירות וציבורי מעות. Tziborei peirot
u-tziborei ma'ot. So מעות. ma'ot. שמע מינה, Shma mina, מנין הוי סימן,
minyan havei siman,
maybe the number of piles qualifies as a סימן siman why? Because
he said ציבורי פירות וציבורי מעות, tziborei peirot v'tziborei ma'ot, that is
the number of piles will be an identifying quality of how to
identify them because not a singular pile. So you have to say
I left two piles of coins or I left four piles of
coins or whatever it is. Okay, okay. So תני ציבור פירות, t'nei
tzibor peirot, it could have taught that you had a singular pile
of fruits. שמע מינה Shma mina מקום הוי סימן. makom havei siman.
No, maybe we could learn that the location is a סימן. siman.
So תני ציבורי פירות. tanei tziborei peirot. So it teaches both, the
plural and the doubling of this kind of a case is basically
to teach you that both the number of piles and where they
are placed, perhaps in relation to each other or placed in general,
would be an identifying סימן. siman. So that is why in this
case even for piles we would say חייב להכריז chayav lehachriz compared
to מפוזרות. mefuzarot. מפוזרות Mefuzarot it's very obvious to the extent that
they are spread out that they are, and we saw that with
that whole density question of, now I'm forgetting which תנא Tanna it
was, which אמורא Amora it was,
a few days ago, that the question of how dense the fruits
are in the ground, that's going to be a question of whether
they're מפוזרות mefuzarot or in ציבורים. tziburim.
It
was רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah was the one that was doing...
Oh, and רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah kept doing all this subdividing. We
have a good רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah today as well. רבי ירמיה
Rabbi Yirmiyah is our friend throughout בבא מציעא. Bava Metzia. Okay. So
next, the next משנה.
Mishna. Meaning, מנין minyan is a סימן, siman, if you found a
ציבור פירות, tzibor peirot, and say there's ten of them, that's a...
Oh no, it's two different questions. Meaning, are we talking about ten
fruits in a pile? Right. Or are we talking about ten piles?
No, I understand, either way מנין minyan should be a סימן, siman,
even if it's ten...
The first one maybe not, meaning because with grain, I'm going to
say what was it Mitch Hedberg, the comedian said, rice is great
when you want to eat two thousand of something. Like
grain, if we're talking about wheat kernels or barley kernels or something,
there's going to be ten thousand.
But there's not ציבורי פירות tziborei peirot though.
So but פירות peirot Rabbi Linzer has been saying the whole time
could also refer to grain. So with grain, you don't know the
number of grains, you know how many kilos of grain you have,
but you don't know the number of grains. So you couldn't say
מנין. minyan.
Oh, so it's not the size, but let's say I did say
oh yeah there were ten apples.
So that probably is a סימן. siman.
That would be a...
Presumably, presumably. But the point that the דיוק diyuk from the משנה
Mishna is that the number of piles, that's why it's ציבורי tziborei
in the plural, to teach you the piles, the number of piles.
Okay. Next סוגיא. sugya. The question about the coins. And here we
have an interesting point noticed by many of the אחרונים Acharonim and
and it's become sort of a popular thing in the academic world
as well as far as I understand is that sometimes we have
תנאים Tannaim and אמוראים Amoraim who like to teach a הלכה halakha
based on their name. So we're going to see. Okay, so the
question is שלושה מטבעות זה על גב זה. shelosha matbe'ot zeh al
gav zeh.
But wait, I think ציבורי פירות tziborei peirot what are we saying
in the end?
We're saying that מנין
הוי סימן minyan havei siman and מקום הוי סימן. makom havei siman.
That we're going both, both.
Yes. So as opposed when we tried to reject it and say
no this is...
At least here this משנה Mishna seems like a good proof for
it, at least as suggested, but maybe it's one or the other
and it's left somewhat unresolved, but it's a good question. Okay. שלושה
מטבעות זה על גב זה. Shelosha matbe'ot zeh al gav zeh. So
we have three coins, one on top of the other. I don't
know what that really means and what it looks like. So we're
going to see what it says. אמר רבי יצחק מגדלאה, Amar Rabbi
Yitzchak Migdala, רבי יצחק מגדלאה Rabbi Yitzchak Migdala said, or just מגדלאה.
Migdala. So כמגדלין, k'migdalin, they're like a tower. tower. So we have
another a number of these kind of eponymic הלכות. halachot. Right, it's
so cool.
It looks like a מגדלא. migdala.
Exactly. All these things. So many many תנאים Tannaim would teach הלכות
halachot that are related to their name, which is just like you
have like a catchphrase, so sometimes your catchphrase—there are many examples. I'm
sure as Sifas points
out here, it's got to be like a Lindor tower.
Something like that. So I'm sure they had that.
And I'm sure
there are a lot of—there are many, many cases of this throughout
ש״ס. Shas. I can't think of any good examples off the top
of my head.
There's something
about—I don't know. I don't remember any examples off the top of
my head, but there are many good examples.
And I think I remember my mother naming
where they—there's two names there and they reference like the הלכה halacha
and they go, we don't know any of these people, we don't
know what their name.
Right, so the names. Right. So sometimes they're nicknames also. So it's
like a nickname that you acquire and then you keep that nickname
based on your הלכות halachot perhaps or vice versa. It becomes interesting.
Yeah.
Okay. והוא שעשויין כמגדלין. vehu she'asuyin kemigdalin. It's like a tower. So
I still don't know what it means. So תניא נמי הכי: tanya
nami hachi: מצא מעות מפוזרות, matza ma'ot mefuzarot, if you found scattered
coins, הרי אלו שלו, harei elu shelo, then they're yours. עשויין כמגדלין,
asuyin kemigdalin, that's the first משנה Mishna in the chapter, but the
ברייתא Braita continues: עשויין כמגדלין, asuyin kemigdalin,
if they're in towers, חייב להכריז, chayav lehachriz, then you have to
return them. ואלו הן עשויין כמגדלין, ve'elu hen asuyin kemigdalin,
what does it mean made like towers? שלושה מטבעות זה על גב
זה. shlosha matbe'ot ze al gav ze. Three coins, one on top
of the other. So it's still—I still don't know. I have two
definitions of what coins it looks like. I mean, it's three coins.
It's one on top of the other. And so I think that
means—what does that—I don't understand. It probably means 1, 2, 3.
That's what I thought it meant. As opposed to a triangle?
So it could be triangle. We're gonna see. It could be other
cases. Yeah, I don't know. It sounds like that's probably what it
is. We're gonna get to that, but it could be more specific
than that. It might have to be that the—we're gonna see the
גמרא Gemara suggests—the largest coin on the bottom going in a—also
that's—we'll
see same size.
Oh, so that's the question. We're gonna get to that. So we
have to keep going. Okay. ואלו הן עשויין כמגדלין שלושה מטבעות זה
על גב זה. ve'elu hen asuyin kemigdalin shlosha matbe'ot ze al gav
ze.
הגופא קשיא. ha gufa kashya. It's still a question. I mean, we
just went in a circle. So אמר מצא מעות מפוזרות הרי אלו
שלו, amar matza ma'ot mefuzarot harei elu shelo, if you found scattered
coins, then they are
yours. הא משלחפי חייב להכריז? ha mishalchafei chayav lehachriz? Maybe the משנה
Mishna had said scattered coins you are yours, but if they are
sort of one on top of the other, they're not so scattered,
then you would have to חייב להכריז? chayav lehachriz? אימא סיפא עשויין
כמגדלין חייב להכריז. eima seifa asuyin kemigdalin chayav lehachriz. The fact that
you have to announce them is only when they're in a tower.
הא משלחפי הרי אלו שלו, ha mishalchafei harei elu shelo, but if
they're somewhat on top of each other, kind of like lopsided, then
you would still be able to keep them.
Just explaining it away.
Exactly. I mean, okay. So תנא כל שאינן עשויין כמגדלין מפוזרות קרי
להו. tana kol she'einan asuyin kemigdalin mefuzarot kari lehu. No, so the
תנא Tanna said anything that's not in a tower counts as scattered.
That's the qualifying point for how scattered is scattered. If they're not
1, 2, 3 on top of each other, that's considered scattered. Okay.
I mean, because if I put down a stack of coins, I'm
saying I'm going to come back and get my stack of coins.
But if I just leave a pile of coins in a—well, not
in a well-defined pile like we saw before, ציבורי מעות, tziburei ma'ot,
but just kind of one on top of the other, then that's
not really meant to be a סימן siman that I'm going to
come back.
Right, unless you made it like a triangle or something, like a
pyramid. That's clearly intention. Yeah.
Okay. That's the pyramid question. So אמר רבי חנינא. amar Rabbi Chanina.
What does Rabbi Chanina say? אמר רבי חנינא לא שנו אלא שלשה
מלכים. amar Rabbi Chanina lo shanu ela shlosha melachim. It's three different
kings. Meaning presumably three different coins, three different types of coins. A
quarter and a nickel and a dime is שלשה מלכים shlosha melachim
because one has whatever Roosevelt and one has—nickel is what? Washington. Washington's
on the quarter. On the nickel is Jefferson. Jefferson. Okay.
Or a buffalo, yeah.
They don't have buffaloes anymore. Okay. שלשה מלכים. shlosha melachim. אבל של
מלך אחד אינו חייב להכריז. aval shel melech echad eino chayav lehachriz.
If they're all three of the same king, you don't have to
return it. So why? היכי דמי? heichi dami? So what are we
talking about? אי דעשויין כמגדלין, ei de'asuyin kemigdalin, if they're made like
a tower, אפילו של מלך אחד נמי? afilu shel melech echad nami?
Then if they're—if they're in a tower, of course I should have
to return them even if they're three different kings? ואי דאין עשויין
כמגדלין, ve'ei de'ein asuyin kemigdalin,
if they're not in a tower, אפילו של שלשה מלכים נמי לא.
afilu shel shlosha melachim nami lo. If it's not in a tower,
I shouldn't have to return it. So who cares how many different
kinds of kings are there? Yeah. Okay. אלא אי איתמר הכי איתמר.
ela ei itmar hachi itmar. This is how you should explain. לא
שנו אלא של מלך אחד כעין שלשה מלכים.
lo shanu ela shel
melech echad ke'ein shlosha melachim. We're talking about even if it's three—if
it's one king but in the style of three different kings. Meaning
what? היכי דמי? heichi dami? דעשויין כמגדלין. de'asuyin kemigdalin.
They're made like a tower. In what sense are they like a
tower? רויחא תתאה, revicha tata'ah, the widest one is on the bottom,
ומציעא עילויה, umetzaya iluyeh,
and then the middle one is on top, or the medium-sized one
on top, וזוטא עילוי מציעא, vezuta ilui metzaya,
and the smallest one on top of the medium-sized one. So like
I said here, this kind of מגדל. migdal. That's the working definition
now of עשויין כמגדלין. asuyin kemigdalin. Even if they have three pictures
of the same king on them, but they're different coins of different
denomination, that would be good. The problem would be if they're all
the same type of coin. This does not count as a
מגדל. migdal. The גמרא Gemara just said no.
But I'm saying, how is it possible that three exactly even, precisely
stacked that way, from different people?
I don't know. It's not that it fell that way. It's that
whether or not you can make a claim that it was intentionally
put. So that's part of the question of the burden of proof.
How strong of a סימן siman do you need? This certainly is
some kind of a סימן; siman; it didn't fall over. But then
that's
the
שלחופי משלוחפי shalkhufei mashloshfei question. How scattered are they? Are they kind
of like one, kind of lopsided? I see. So he said, a
מגדלים migdalim is like this, and like—so it's also just interesting for
מגדל בבל, Migdal Bavel, right? We think about מגדל בבל Migdal Bavel
often like this kind of a tower. Maybe מגדל בבל Migdal Bavel
was more of this kind of a tower, like a more step-sided
pyramid type shape.
Not
like the Empire State Building.
Like a ziggurat. Like a pyramid. Like the Aztec, something like that.
Right, like a pyramid, except it's close up.
A little bit.
So but I'm trying to understand.
You say if it's like this, you
have—if it's like this, the working assumption now is that you don't
have to return. But why? 'Cause this is not a good enough
סימן. siman. According to רבי חנינא, Rabbi Chanina, that's not a good
enough סימן. siman. I don't understand it either. That's just what רבי
חנינא Rabbi Chanina said. Let's keep going. Okay. תא שמע. Ta shema.
דאמרינן de-amrinan אנוחי אנחיה, anochei anchei,
that you assume that the person put them like that. אבל של
מלך אחד, Aval shel melech echad, if they're all the same denomination,
the same size, דכולהו כי הדדי נינהו, de-kulehu ke-hadadi ninhu, that they're
all identical, אף על גב דמנחי אהדדי, af al gav de-manchei a-hadadi,
the fact that they're one on top of the other, הרי אלו
שלו. harei elu shelo. You get to keep them. Okay. אימה, Eima,
איתרמויי איתרמי ובהדי הדדי נפיל. itramuyei itrami u-be-hadei hadadi nefil.
Yes,
because maybe איתרמויי איתרמי ובהדי הדדי נפיל. itramuyei itrami u-be-hadei hadadi nefil.
Maybe they were one on top of the other and they fell
all together. Okay, meaning you can presume that. Meaning the burden of
proof in that kind of a case
is higher to be able to make the סימן siman claim. Okay.
Yes, Charlie's question.
Ancient Jewish coins never had pictures on them.
Well, that's a question. We have the סוגיא sugya about אברהם אבינו
Avraham Avinu and שרה's Sarah's coin that had a young couple on
it.
But it didn't have pictures of people.
Well, but אברהם אבינו's Avraham Avinu's coin did have people on it.
No, but בר כוכבא's Bar Kochba's coins didn't have people and things
like that. They had
a—חשמונאים, Chashmonaim, right, that's the proof that the מנורה Menorah had the
curved branches. Don't let Chabad hear me say that. But okay. So...
what? הרמב"ם. Ha-Rambam. הרמב"ם Ha-Rambam and רש"י Rashi never saw a picture
of the מנורה. Menorah. If they had seen a picture of the
מנורה, Menorah, they would have agreed.
They saw it under Rome. They didn't.
It's on the Arch of Titus, on the coins. רבי יוחנן אמר
אפילו של מלך אחד נמי מכריז. Rabbi Yochanan amar afillu shel melech
echad nami machriz. Ah, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan disagrees with רבי חנינא.
Rabbi Chanina. He says if even if it's of one king, meaning
of the same size, you do have to return it, Michael's coins.
So מאי מכריז? mai machriz? What does it mean to be
מכריז? machriz? So... I mean, מאי מכריז? mai machriz? מנין. Minyan. So...
מאי איריא תלתא? mai irya tlata? So three on top of two,
do you have to return?
מאי איריא תלתא? אפילו תרי. Mai irya tlata? Afillu terei.
So what—sorry, why are we saying three specifically? Right, אפילו תרי, afillu
terei, even if it's two, meaning if it's one, two, this kind
of a tower. Just two coins stacked on top of each other.
A very short tower. Okay. So אמר רבינא, Amar Ravina, so רבינא
Ravina says back to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, so
טיבעא מכריז—no, tiba machriz טיבעא מכריז. tiba machriz.
So טיבעא מכריז, tiba machriz, that you have to—that at some point,
basically you have to be able to announce and at some point
not. Meaning, what does רש"י Rashi say? מטבעות מצאתי, matbe'ot matzati, I
found coins. So הכא תרי לאו סימנא הוא. hacha terei lav simana
hu. Two is not enough of a סימן. siman. דמיעוט מטבעות. demi'ut
matbe'ot.
It's like so few coins. Two coins is not enough to be
able to announce. You need a sort of an enough—enough quantity to
be able to announce it. Okay. בעא רב ירמיה, Ba'ei Rav Yirmiyah,
רב ירמיה's Rav Yirmiyah's question. So כשיר מאי? kashir mai? In the
shape of a שיר? shir? Like in a circle perhaps or in
some kind of other shapes. Oh, yes, oh perfect. Using בר כוכבא
Bar Kochba coins.
Wonderful. So Steinsaltz edition has pictures. So כשיר מאי? kashir mai? If
it's like a—like a or like a camel train where they circle
around in a circle.
Okay. כשורה מאי? keshura mai?
Like a שיירא. shayara. So מאי? mai? כשורה, keshura, or if they're
in a straight line, horizontally, מאי? mai? כחצובה מאי? ke-chatzuva mai? Or
if they're in a—כחצובה ke-chatzuva is like a triangular shape, right? So
מאי? mai? Or כסולם מאי? ke-sulam mai? If they're in a ladder
shape. I don't know what it means that coins are stacked in
a ladder shape. I wish I had a picture. Okay. מאי? mai?
So... this here.
So רב ירמיה's Rav Yirmiyah's question. He says מאי? mai? If they're
all in another kind of shape besides the מגדלים migdalim case, right?
So פשוט מהא דאמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה. pashut me-ha
de-amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha. So we have an opinion
from רב נחמן Rav Nachman quoting רבה בר אבוה. Rabbah bar Avuha.
כל שאילו מכניס לה קיסם ביניהן ונוטלן בבת אחת, kol she-ilu machnis
la keisam beineihen ve-notlan be-vat achat, if you could put a splinter
of wood underneath and lift them up all together... okay... חייב להכריז.
chayav l'hachriz. In other words, that somehow the structure of the coins
is solid enough that it could be transported together. I'm not exactly
sure then about the triangle and about the circle. Like I would
have to do a lot of tests at home. Like you put
coins... I'm not exactly sure then about the triangle and about the
circle like I would have to do a lot of tests at
home like you put coins on the table and you slide a
paper underneath and you lift it up, does it move around? That's
kind of the question.
Okay, ורש"י פירש סולא v'Rashi peirush sula means some French word that
sounds like
elevator. Escalo-nay.
Escalo, yeah, escalator. And a manual escalator. You have to climb up
on the steps.
Escalone.
Escalo. Echelon. Echelons, echelons is steps, yeah. Okay, echelon. Okay good.
כסא דמכניס לה קיסמא ביניהן ונוטלן
בבת אחת חייב להכריז.
kissa d'machnis
lah
kaisma beineihen v'notlan b'vas achas chayav l'hachriz. So by רב אשי. Rav
Ashi. רב אשי Rav Ashi asked כאבני בית קולס. k'avnei beis kulus.
It's like the stones of the house of קולס. Kulus. So what
is קולס? Kulus? Look in רש"י. Rashi. מרקוליס. Markulis. מרקוליס Markulis is
the name we're familiar with, is the name of a Roman עבודה
זרה, avodah zarah, probably is the Roman god Mercurius with a strange
accent. So מרקוליס, Markulis, and they would throw rocks at the statue
of מרקוליס Markulis and that was the way it was worshipped, which
is an interesting question comes up in ההלכה ha'halachah which is that
there are certain types of עבודה avodah you do for עבודה זרה
avodah zarah is universal. Any kind of עבודה זרה avodah zarah if
you sacrifice something, if you bow to it, things like that, that
would be עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. And then also if you do
the עבודה avodah designated for that idol, then also counts as עבודה
זרה. avodah zarah. So in that case, throwing a rock at מרקוליס.
Markulis. But if you throw a rock at some other עבודה זרה
avodah zarah where it's not meant to be, well, that's very disrespectful,
so that wouldn't be עבודה זרה avodah zarah for that type of
idols, only for if that's the designated worship of that god, yes.
I looked up free dictionary online. Escalone in Old French is the
rungs of a ladder.
Rungs of a ladder. Okay. So I'm not sure again on how
how do you make
coins- they probably got that from רש"י. Rashi.
But what does it mean that the rungs of a ladder the
coins are arranged like a rungs of a ladder? I'm not sure.
Okay. So it's overlapping.
Overlapping. Okay. Or maybe like that. Like a staircase. Okay. So it's
like a staircase, it's not like the rungs of a ladder. Okay.
כאבני בית קולס. k'avnei beis kulus. So רב אשי Rav Ashi says
it's like the coins, the stones of מרקוליס. Markulis. So תוספות Tosafot
has an interesting question. How come we're allowed to call the עבודה
זרה avodah zarah by its name? Because we have a הלכה halachah
לא יזכר על פיך lo yizacher al picha you're not allowed to
mention the names of different types of עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So
there are obviously many ones that get mentioned in the גמרא. Gemara.
So תוספות Tosafot says the reason why is because the name of
the עבודה זרה avodah zarah actually isn't מרקוליס, Markulis, it's actually קולס,
Kulus, and then it's a קשיא kashya on this סוגיא sugya because
here it's called בית קולס Beis Kulus and here it's calling him
by name. So anyway,
whatever. Something like that.
בית קולס. Beis Kulus.
קולס Kulus maybe קולס Kulus is קילוס, kilus, something, whatever. Okay. מה
תא שמע דתניא מצא מעות מפוזרות הרי אלו שלו. Ma ta shema
d'tanya matza ma'os mefuzaros harei elu shelo. If you found scattered coins,
they are yours. Okay. כאבני בית קולס חייב להכריז. k'avnei beis kulus
chayav l'hachriz.
If they are like the stones of the worship of מרקוליס, Markulis,
then you have to announce them. ואלו הן ואלו
הן אבני בית קולס אחת מכאן ואחת מכאן ואחת על גביהן. v'eilu
hein v'eilu hein avnei beis kulus achas mikan v'achas mikan v'achas al
gabeihen.
It means another kind of tower. One here and one here and
one in the middle. Right. So that's the third kind. That's בית
קולס Beis Kulus type.
This is the picture on the front.
No, that must- must be something else. That's different. That must be
something else
on the front.
Okay. כאבני בית קולס חייב להכריז ואלו הן אבני בית קולס אחת
מכאן ואחת מכאן ואחת על גביהן. k'avnei beis kulus chayav l'hachriz v'eilu
hein avnei beis kulus achas mikan v'achas mikan v'achas al gabeihen. תנו
רבנן המוצא סלע בשוק ומצאו חבירו ואמר לו שלי היא. Tanu rabanan
hamotza sela bashuk u'metza'o chaveiro v'amar lo sheli hi. If you found
a coin in the
marketplace and your friend found you and said to you it's mine,
it's my coin, and he tries to make a claim. סימן. Siman.
What kind of סימנים simanim does he try? חדשה היא. Chadasha hi.
It's brand new. Or נירונית היא. Nironis hi. It has Nero's face
on it. Okay. של מלך פלוני היא. shel melech ploni hi. It's
from a certain kind of king.
Okay. ולא אמר כלום. v'lo amar klum. Those don't count as סימנים
simanim because if I say, if I find a quarter and then
someone comes to me and says I lost a quarter, it has
George Washington on it, that's not a proof of anything because the
point is that all coins are totally fungible. Now it's very interesting
by כלי, kli, we would treat that as as a סימן. siman.
The point is that coins change hands much more than כלים keilim
or much more than any kind of thing. Right? Imagine, think about
it. Right? What does it say?
Okay, ולא כלום v'lo klum even if his name is engraved into
the coin. Right? I imagine people might have done that for, you
know, a very valuable coin. You could scratch your name into the
metal. Okay. ולא אמר כלום. lo amar klum. It doesn't say anything.
Why? לפי שאין סימן למטבע. lefi she'ein siman l'matbei'ah. There's no such
thing as a סימן siman for a coin. Why? דאמר דילמא אפוקי
אפקיה. d'amar dilma afokei afkeih. He spent it already. ומאיניש אחרינא נפל.
u'me'enish achrina nafal. Someone else must have lost it. Meaning, you can't
claim that's my lucky coin, it has my name Dan carved into
it, because I say no, you spent it at the vending machine,
the vending machine company put it in the bank, the bank gave
it out to somebody else in a roll of quarters, and now
you know, this other guy had it and dropped it. Who says?
So it's different than a כלי. kli. A כלי, kli, if you
can identify the סימן siman on a כלי, kli, now how can
we not say the same thing? You sold your כלי kli to
someone else and now he lost it. Because presumably the amount of
familiarity you have with a כלי kli would be that you would
be able to recognize it that it was yours. We have a
different kind of assumption about coins compared to כלים. keilim. The next
משנה mishnah says... משנה mishnah says מצא אחר הגפה, matza achar hagafah,
you found something behind a fence, behind a wall, או אחר הגדר,
o achar hageder, or behind a wall, גוזלות מקושרים. gozalot mekusharim. You
found little birds that have been tied up together. Presumably these are
live birds that are bound together in, like little pigeons that have
been tied together in some way. Alright. Or או בשבילין שבשדה, o
bishvilin shebasadeh, or in the paths through the field, הרי זה לא
יגע בהן, harei zeh lo yigah bahen, do not touch them. That's
an interesting הלכה. halacha. We haven't seen that before. We've seen הרי
אלו שלו, harei elu shelo, we've seen הרי אלו חייב להכריז. harei
elu chayav lehachriz. This is לא יגע בהן, lo yigah bahen, you
don't touch them. Sounds like what the תורה torah said לא יוכל
להתעלם, lo yuchal lehitalem, you can't ignore it. It sounds like here
you have to ignore it. Interesting point. Okay, מצא כלי באשפה, matza
kli be'ashpah, you found a כלי, kli, a vessel, in the trash
pile. אם מכוסה, im mechuseh, if it was totally covered, לא יגע
בו, lo yigah bo, then you cannot take it, you can't touch
it. אם מגולה, im megulah, if it was uncovered a little bit,
נוטל ומכריז, notel u'machriz, then you take it out and you have
to announce it like any other lost כלי. kli. Now we're going
to see the גמרא gemara is going to figure out what are
we talking about here. Okay, מאי טעמא דאמרינן הני איניש אצנינהו, mai
ta'ama de'amrinan hanei inish atzninehu, maybe a person went and hid them
there. Meaning that's why they're there. The little birds were hidden behind
the wall, the כלי kli was tucked inside the trash pile as
a hiding place. Okay, we're going to have to see why that
makes sense. ואי שקיל להו, ve'ee shakil lehu, if you take it,
לית להו למרייהו סימנא בגווייהו, leit lehu lemareihu simana begaveihu, because then
once you've moved it you've taken away the סימן. siman. Why? Because
these are things which don't have a סימן siman of their own
presumably. The only סימן siman is I hid it in the trash
pile or I put it behind the fence. It's a סימן במקום.
siman bamakom. So if you move it, if you touch it, even
in order to try to return it, then you've taken away the
סימן siman of the owner. Okay, הלכך לשבקינהו עד דאתי למרייהו ושקיל
להו. hilchach leshavkinehu ad de'ati lemareihu veshakil lehu. So then you basically
got yourself into a situation where now you have to wait for
him to come to take it. ואמאי להוי קשר סימנא, ve'amai lehavei
kesher simana, maybe the knot in the rope holding the birds together
should be a סימן siman in itself? אמר רבי אבא בר זבדא
אמר רב במקושרים בכנפיהם. amar rabbi abba bar zavda amar rav bimkusharim
bichenfeihem.
No, it's when they're tied by their wings, דכולי עלמא הכי מתקשר
להו, dekulei alma hachi mitkasher lehu, because like everybody does it kind
of the same way, I guess.
Okay, ולהוי מקום סימן, velehavei makom siman, so maybe the place should
be the סימן. siman. So אמר רב עוקבא בר חמא במדדים, amar
rav ukva bar chama bimdadim, so where the birds are still able
to kind of like wiggle waggle around. The birds can walk around
a little bit. Okay, in other words that the מקום makom is
not a סימן siman because the birds were wandering. Okay, אי במדדים
מעלמא אתו
ומותרים.
ee bimdadim me'alma
atu umutarim. So then if they're walking around then they're totally fair
game because they're not restricted in any way, then you should be
able to take them. So איכא למימר מעלמא אתו, ika lemeimar me'alma
atu, maybe they came from somewhere else, right? They arrived from somewhere
else. ואיכא למימר איניש אצנינהו והוי ליה ספק הינוח, ve'ika lemeimar inish
atzninehu vehavei leh safek hinuach, and maybe, meaning I don't know whether
the birds wandered over here from somewhere else or if the owner
put them here because the birds are still able to wander around
a little bit.
Therefore it's ספק מקום סימן. safek makom siman. Exactly, it's ספק הינוח.
safek hinuach. Maybe it was put down. ואמר רב אבא בר זבדא
אמר רב כל ספק הינוח לכתחילה לא יטול ואם נטל לא יחזיר.
ve'amar rav abba bar zavda amar rav kol safek hinuach l'chat'chila lo
yitol ve'im natal lo yachzir. So you get yourself into a difficult
situation because there's sort of no way to resolve this. What does
it mean לא יחזיר? lo yachzir? If you look at what רש"י
rashi says, דהא ליכא דהאי סימנא, deha lika de'hai simana, no one
can come and claim it because you don't have a סימן. siman.
So if the owner tries to come and get it from you,
you don't give it back to him. That's what רש"י rashi says
לא יחזיר. lo yachzir. The רמב"ם rambam says interestingly not like that.
The רמב"ם rambam says לא יחזיר lo yachzir means someone else tries
to claim it from you, not that he doesn't have a סימן
siman because he says, sorry, the רמב"ם rambam and רש"י rashi seem
to agree, but the ראב"ד ra'avad and תוספות tosafot each,
those who argue with each other, both try to say לא יחזיר
lo yachzir means almost the opposite, that if you take it at
that point you don't get to keep it, but you also can't
give it back to him, you just have to watch it all
the time and you're a שומר shomer for it, but you don't
get to use it forever. Forever and you're stuck because you have
an obligation to return it but you also don't have the ability
to return it because the owner cannot, cannot make a claim for
it because he has no סימן. siman.
The other way of reading לא יגע בהם lo yigah bahen is
לכתחילה l'chat'chila leave it because of the ספק מקום סימן safek makom
siman or ספק הינוח. safek hinuach.
Right, that's what he says. Right.
But בדיעבד bedi'avad if you take it it's yours.
Well, but what does לא יחזיר lo yachzir mean? So רש"י rashi
and the רמב"ם rambam read it exactly like that. תוספות tosafot and
the ראב"ד ra'avad say לא יחזיר lo yachzir means not you get
to keep it but you have to watch it.
יהא במקומו? yehe bimkomo?
No, you can bring it with you but you can't use it
because it's a מציאה metziah that you're obligated to return but the
owner cannot, cannot claim it from you. Okay. So מצא כלי באשפה
מכוסה לא יגע בו מגולה נוטל ומכריז. matza kli be'ashpah mechuseh lo
yigah bo megulah notel u'machriz. If you found a כלי kli in
the trash, so then if it was covered don't touch it. מגולה,
megulah, if it was uncovered you can take it and you have
to announce it, that is you have to return it.
ורמינהו *urminhu*, מצא
כלי טמון באשפה *matza kli tamun be'ashpa*. If you found a כלי
*kli* that was hidden inside the trash, נוטל ומכריז *notel umachriz*, you
can take it and you have to announce it, שכן דרך אשפה
ashpa לפנות *sheken derech ashpa lifnot* because the trash pile gets cleaned
out all the time. So even if a person had put it
there, so then it was going to see it's not going to
make any sense. So אמר רב זביד Rav Zevid *amar Rav Zvid*,
לא קשיא *lo kashya*. So meaning what are we talking about? If
the trash pile is going to be cleaned out regularly, so then
the person would have had יאוש *yeush* because you put it in
the trash, you hid it in the trash, even if you hid
it in the trash it's going to get cleaned out, so you're
not going to be able to come back and get it. So
that's not going to be a good place to hide your things.
So that's what we're going to see. So אמר רב זביד *amar
Rav Zvid*, לא קשיא *lo kashya*, הא בכובא וכסי והא בסכיני והמנק
*ha bechuve uchese veha besakine vehimnak*, ובכובא וכסי *uvechuve
uchese*.
So כובא וכסי *chuve uchese* are larger containers, and a סכיני *sakine*
knives, והמנק *vehimnak* and the fork. Right? We have סוכה *Sukkah*, סוכות
*Succos* as well, right? חול המועד *Chol HaMoed*. So one of the
פסול *pasul* kinds of לולב *lulav* is if the תיומת *tiyomet* of
the לולב *lulav* is as a המנק *himnak* thing, which probably means
it looks like a fork. It probably means it looks like this.
That is, it's not split perfectly 50-50, but it's split one side
is crooked off to the side. So that's פסול *pasul* for a
לולב *lulav*. So always have to put in a little bit עניינא
דיומא *inyana dyoma*. Okay. So בסכיני והמנק *besakine vehimnak*. So if it
was like a knife and forks, נוטל ומכריז *notel umachriz*. Then you
have to take them and announce them. So what's the difference? Because
a large כלי *kli*, if you throw away a large כלי *kli*,
then or if you tried to hide a large כלי *kli* in
the trash, it's going to get thrown away. But if you hid
small things there, maybe that was something that you were planning to
just hide there. So you have, they have a סימן *siman*, they
can come and claim.
Yeah, and am I missing something? The one הלכה *halacha* that we
don't have is that if it's in the trash, it's הפקר *hefker*
you can take it.
Correct, it does not sound like that.
It doesn't sound, like I got a thousand, right? What is this
אשפה *ashpa*?
Right, and what does it mean in אשפה *ashpa*? So it means
in אשפה *ashpa*, so we're going to get to that. Presumably it
means in אשפה *ashpa* that does not get cleaned out regularly. So
it's a good place to hide things. It's like a big pile
of stuff.
Right, normally you think if it's tossed it would be הפקר *hefker*
without question. Right.
So that's a question. I found something in the trash can. Right,
what does that mean? So we're going to see. Okay. So בכובא
וכסי לא קשיא *bechuve uchese lo kashya*. כאן באשפה העשויה לפנות *kan
be'ashpa ha'asuya lifnot*, one is talking about a case where the אשפה
*ashpa* will be regularly cleared out, taken to the dump. כאן באשפה
שאינה עשויה לפנות *kan be'ashpa she'eina asuya lifnot*, it was not regularly
cleared out, like that's where the trash is going to stay. So
hiding things would be a good idea. אשפה העשויה לפנות *ashpa ha'asuya
lifnot* if it's a trash pile that's usually moved, אבידה מדעת *aveida
mida'at*. Right, if it's going to get thrown away, that's אבידה מדעת
*aveida mida'at*, that's יאוש מדעת *yeush mida'at*. So that everyone agrees the
person who finds it, finders keepers. Okay. אלא באשפה שאינה עשויה לפנות
*ela be'ashpa she'eina asuya lifnot*, it must be a trash pile that
is not normally cleaned out. ונמלך עליה לפנותה *venimlach aleha lifnotah*, and
then the owner of the חצר *chatzer* decided finally to take out
the trash. Right, this is like Arlo Guthrie's Alice's Restaurant, it's almost
Thanksgiving time, right? The trash was full in the church. Okay. באשפה
שאינה עשויה לפנות ונמלך עליה לפנותה *be'ashpa she'eina asuya lifnot venimlach aleha
lifnotah*. בשלמא למר בר רב פפא *bishlama lemar bar Rav Pappa*, דהיינו
דקתני *dehaynu de'katni*, שכן דרך אשפה לפנות *sheken derech ashpa lifnot*. So
רב פפא *Rav Pappa* makes sense because the normally trash, you normally
do take out the trash. אלא לרב זביד *ela leRav Zvid*, but
what about רב זביד *Rav Zvid*? רב זביד *Rav Zvid* said the
whole distinction was what kind of כלי *kli* it was. So his
position doesn't make sense. So מאי שכן דרך אשפה לפנות *mai sheken
derech ashpa lifnot*? What does it mean that the trash is normally
taken out? שכן דרך אשפה לפנות לה כלים keilim. קטנים *sheken derech
ashpa lifnot lah kelim ktanim*. No, you take out the trash, you
take out the small stuff from the trash, but the huge stuff,
huge piles in the trash, that you leave. I guess that's the
point, which is that רב זביד *Rav Zvid* has to be able
to say that it's a trash pile that even when you clear
it out, you don't clear out everything. It still stays the trash
pile, you just
only take the small stuff out. And therefore if it was small
כלים keilim *kelim*, you wouldn't be a good idea to hide them
there because the opposite, רב זביד *Rav Zvid* said you'd be able
to assume that it was that it was what is it? אבידה
מדעת *aveida mida'at* and it would be הפקר *hefker* because you'd be
thrown out.
It would be removed. There would be a פינוי *pinui*. But now
I'm confused. No, it sounds like the small stuff, because רב זביד
*Rav Zvid* says that the small stuff חייב להכריז *chayav lehachriz*, right?
And the large stuff לא יגע בהם *lo yiga bahem*. So the
לא יגע בהם *lo yiga bahem* means that it's a ספק הינוח
*safek hinuach*. We don't know whether it was lost or whether it
was הפקר *hefker* and thrown out in the trash or whether it's
being hidden there. But the small things חייב להכריז *chayav lehachriz* means
for sure we know that they were put there. That means that
it's a trash pile that normally gets cleaned out and that normally
you don't put small things in the trash. Therefore if you found
something small in the
trash, I think that's
what רש"י *Rashi* is saying, right? It's so counterintuitive.
It is a bit counter, it's very different than how we relate
to trash piles. There's got to be a פינוי *pinui*.
Every other day they come and they empty the thing and they
pour it into the Mediterranean. That sounds like אבידה מדעת *aveida mida'at*.
That's אבידה מדעת *aveida mida'at* for sure. The question is whether it
means do you take your trash out of your house and dump
it in this pile, but would
that have your fork and knife in it?
No, your fork and knife you didn't mean to put in the
trash. So that's what he's talking about. That you could be that
somebody would have put these little things right in there. It must
have been by accident. It must have been a mistake. Find somebody's
checkbook in the trash, it's an אבידה. You know, that kind of
a thing. Something small and valuable that could have gotten mixed. Right.
Your bicycle. Right, a bicycle you put in the trash, you intended
it to be, right. So מגולה מכוסה meguoleh mechusseh basically got ignored,
right. That's an interesting distinction, right? The משנה Mishnah talked about or
the ברייתא Braitah talked about, oh, it was covered, it was uncovered,
whatever, yeah, it was in the משנה. Mishnah. That but it was
sort of don't care, meaning that just comes to be, that comes
to indicate really what we're talking about is אשפה דרך אשפה לפנות
ashpa derech ashpa lifnot or not, whether it's a trash that gets
taken out. So that's meaning the מכוסה מגולה mechusseh meguoleh isn't really
discussed here, it becomes transposed into that distinction about the or for
רב זביד about the different kinds of כלים. keilim So it's not
actually meaning it's very interesting what happened. We had a משנה Mishnah
that had an explicit criterion: if it's covered by trash or if
it's a bit uncovered, right? And they said no, no, no, that's
not what we're talking about. Really we're talking about big כלים and
small כלים or we're talking about different kinds of trash. But neither
of them cares about how deep in the trash you buried it,
right? What happened? Right, a person came, if it's totally buried inside
it means you went and hid it there, but if it was
kind of just sticking out it means that someone threw it away
and it fell in the trash, right? That's what the משנה Mishnah
is saying. But then the two אמוראים Amoraim seem to reject that
distinction. The reality of what אשפות ashpot were might have changed. That's
also true. I mean we don't know our אשפה but that's right.
Our trash is very different. Like a pile of pottery somewhere. Yeah,
they do. Well and archaeologists love finding trash piles because you find
all sorts of very interesting things in the trash. Like coins. Like
coins, like all broken containers and things. The stuff that people wanted
to keep got stolen, got burned, got sold, got went off somewhere,
but in the trash you have a big pile of stuff all
in one place. So it's a good place to look for archaeology.
The next משנה, Mishnah, we can go a little bit a few
more minutes. מצא בגל, matza be-gal, you found something in a pile
of rocks. או בכותל ישן, o bekosel yashan, or in an old
wall that soon will be a pile of rocks. Okay. הרי אלו
שלו, harei eilu shelo, then you can keep them. מצא בכותל חדש,
matza bekosel chadash, if you found something in a new wall, and
we're going to understand what that means, we know from the משנה
Mishnah in פסחים Pesachim and things like that, they had little hidey-holes
in their walls. So a little cubbyhole in the wall, that's where
you would hide something, so if you find something in a כותל
חדש kosel chadash it means someone put it there. So מחציו ולחוץ,
mechetzo lachutz, if it's from halfway point to the outside of the
wall, שלו, shelo, then you can keep it because the householder only
puts things in a hidey-hole right close to his house, right, not
in the outside wall. Okay. מחציו ולפנים, mechetzo ulefanim, if it's from
the halfway inside, של בעל הבית, shel ba'al habayit, then it belongs
to the householder. אם היה משכירו לאחרים, im haya maskiro leachairim, if
you rented the house to other people, אפילו בתוך הבית afilu betoch
habayit הרי אלו שלו. harei eilu shelo. If it's a rental property,
then any objects that get lost even inside the house because you
don't know whose house, who was renting the house, so you don't
know whose ownership it is. A person who rents a house and
they leave something behind, they say forget about it, I'm never going
to get it back, I left it on vacation or whatever, so
they're not going to be able to come back and claim it.
If it's someone who lives in the house, then it obviously belongs
to the בעל הבית. ba'al habayit. Are the apertures in the wall
all the way through so that you're talking about the depth from
the outside to halfway or from the inside to halfway? That's a
good question. Meaning are we talking about if this is the wall...
It's like a window. Right, is it like this and like this
or is it just one tube and then the question is we
have to draw an imaginary line? I don't know that answer. That's
a good question. It may be a מחלוקת. machloket. I'm not sure.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, תני דנא שיכול לומר לו שאמוריים
הם, tani dena she-yachol lomar lo she-Emori-im heim, meaning you can always
claim if it was in an old wall that the lost object
belonged to the אמוריים, Emori-im, not the אמוראים, Amoraim, the אמוריים, Emori-im,
the Amorites, the כנענים Kena'anim who lived in the land. So אטו
אמוריים מטמני ישראל לא מטמני? atu Emori-im matnyei Yisrael lo matnyei? Does
that mean that only Canaanites hide things in the wall but not
Israelites? So לא צריכה lo tzericha דשייך טפי, de-shaich tfei, it must
be that it was like very hidden inside the pile, right? Or
חלוד חלודה, halud haluda, it got very buried, it got very contained
or it was in some kind of container, those kind of things.
So I mean all this stuff gets into very interesting questions about
like I was saying before, we'll stop here, but just the question
of archaeology and things like that or tomb raiders and things like
that, right? Like what happens? The king of Egypt is buried with
all sorts of fancy stuff and then they lock up the tomb
forever and then a bunch of archaeologists come and claim it for
the British Museum, right? So does that belong to the British Museum?
Does that belong to the modern Egyptians? No, it's cultural theft. It's
cultural theft in a sense of like oh we, but who actually
owns that? No one alive is descendant of this person or has
any real claim to those objects. That's like something hidden in an
old wall. It becomes difficult to make a real property claim. You
have to start making cultural arguments and things like that. It belongs
to the national heritage of the place where it's located and things
like that, but it becomes an interesting question. So we'll leave it.
That category itself. Well exactly, we have the UN and we have
all sorts of treaties. That category itself of the cultural heritage of
the nation. Well right, that's not a well... exactly, exactly, the idea
of nationality. To take back property-wise everything that some force stole from
them. There's cases now in museums where they're forcing them to return.
Exactly, and it's a major question, what are they going to do?
Exactly, it's a major question. So we'll stop here, everyone should have
חג שמח Chag Sameach מועדים לשמחה. Moadim L'simcha.